Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 700, 2002-2003
    - "Law and Order: Civil Liberties and the War on Terrorism" No. UK717, 2002 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 14; Digital Betacam, box 82)
      Erwin Chemerinsky, Sydney M. Irmas professor of public interest law, legal ethics, and political science, University of Southern California, and Eugene Volokh, professor of law, University of California, Los Angeles. Does the war on terrorism threaten our civil liberties? Benjamin Franklin famously admonished, "They that can give up essential liberty to obtain a little temporary safety deserve neither liberty nor safety." Are we today being asked to give up essential liberties for temporary safety? If so, is it worth it? Or are the fears that the government's war on terrorism will trample our freedoms overblown?
    - "Out for a Constitutional: The Supreme Court and the Constitution" No. UK718, 2002 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 83)
      Erwin Chemerinsky, Sydney M. Irmas professor of public interest law, legal ethics, and political science, University of Southern California; and John Eastman, associate professor and director of the Center for Constitutional Jurisprudence, Chapman University. The Supreme Court has the final authority on all matters of law under the U.S. Constitution. But what legal philosophy should the Supreme Court use to reach its decisions? Should the Court merely hand down rules based on the text of a fixed, or "dead," Constitution? Or should the Court apply standards that are based on interpretations of a "living" Constitution that evolves as our society changes? These fundamentally different approaches to constitutional law have created a rift with the current Supreme Court. How serious is this rift? Who's right? And to what extent are these competing arguments merely cover for ideological positions?
    - "Worth the Fighting For: A Conversation with John McCain" No. UK719, 2002 November 7 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 83)
      John McCain, Republican senator, Arizona. John McCain has spent a lifetime in the service of his country, including twenty-two years as a naval aviator, two terms in the United States House of Representatives, and service in the United States Senate, since 1986. Following his 2000 presidential campaign and the hard-fought passage of his Campaign Finance Bill, John McCain reflects on a life in politics in his recent memoir, Worth the Fighting For. A lifelong Republican, Senator McCain has broken with his party's mainstream on a number of issues in recent years. Does John McCain still consider himself a conservative? And why does McCain so often play the maverick?
    - "Attack of the Clones: The Ethics of Human Cloning" No. UK720, 2002 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 83)
      Leon Kass, chairman, President's Council on Bioethics, Addie Clark Harding professor, College and the Committee on Social Thought, University of Chicago, and author, Life, Liberty and the Defense of Dignity: The Challenge for Bioethics; and Gregory Stock, director, Program on Medicine, Technology, and Society, UCLA School of Medicine, and author, Redesigning Humans: Our Inevitable Genetic Future. Cloning, using biotechnology to create embryos with specific genetic information, identical to other embryos or even human adults, used to sound like science fiction. Today, however, the ability to successfully clone human embryos is a matter of when, not if. But should human cloning be allowed to go forward? Is cloning morally wrong, in and of itself? Should we make a distinction between cloning for medical research and cloning for procreation? If cloning is morally wrong, could we stop it even if we wanted to? And if cloning isn't or can't be banned, how should it be regulated?
    - "Going Around in Circles: The Future of NASA" No. UK721, 2002 October 25 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 83)
      Chris Chyba, codirector, Center for International Security and Cooperation, Stanford University, and Carl Sagan chair for the study of life in the universe, SETI Institute; Timothy Ferris, author, Seeing in the Dark: How Backyard Stargazers Are Probing Deep Space and Guarding Earth from Interplanetary Peril; and David Morrison, senior scientist, NASA Astrobiology Institute. The space program used to mean one thing: the effort to put American astronauts on the moon. That effort is becoming ancient history. We haven't sent anyone to the moon in thirty years. So what is NASA's mission today? What sort of space exploration is worth pursuing today and tomorrow? And is NASA the right institution for the job?
    - "With Death Do Us Part? Reforming the Death Penalty" No. UK722, 2002 November 7 (Folder VHS, box 15; 1", loose on shelf; Digital Betacam, box 84)
      Alex Kozinski, judge, United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit and Scott Turow, author, Reversible Errors, member, Illinois Governor's Commission on Capital Punishment, and attorney and partner, Sonnenschein, Nath & Rosenthal. It's been more than 25 years since the Supreme Court reinstated the death penalty in 1976. For most of that time, the number of executions in this country climbed steadily higher. In the past several years, however, the death penalty has come under increasing criticism. Executions have fallen nationwide from a high of 98 in 1998 to 66 in 2001. Two states, Illinois and Maryland, declared moratoria on the death penalty over concerns that the death penalty could not be administered fairly. Is the death penalty immoral in and of itself? If not, is it unconstitutional? What is required to ensure that the death penalty is administered with fairness, justice, and accuracy?
    - "Pulling Out the Roots: The Roots of Terrorism" No. UK723, 2002 November 11 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 84)
      Paul Wilkinson, chairman and director, Center for the Study of Terrorism and Political Violence, University of St. Andrews and Robert Wright, contributing editor, The New Republic, Time Magazine, and Slate, and author, Nonzero: The Logic of Human Destiny. What are the root causes of terrorism and how should we respond to them? If the discontent and hatred that breed terrorism spring from economic, political, and cultural grievances, should we address those grievances? Or does acknowledgment of these types of causes of terrorism lend a dangerous legitimacy to terrorists themselves?
    - "The Skeptical Environmentalist: Measuring the State of the Environment" No. UK724, 2002 November 12 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 84)
      Daniel Kammen, professor of energy and society, Energy and Resources Group, University of California, Berkeley, and director, Renewable and Appropriate Energy Laboratory and Bjørn Lomborg, author, The Skeptical Environmentalist: Measuring the Real State of the World and associate professor of statistics, University of Aarhus. Global warming, population, deforestation, mass extinctions--according to environmental groups and environmental scientists, the earth is in ever more dire straits. Should we heed these warnings and take steps to mitigate our impact on the global ecosystem? Danish statistician Bjørn Lomborg has come forward to say, not so fast. He claims the environmental state of the world is actually improving, not getting worse. His claims have generated a firestorm of condemnation in the scientific community. Why? And how can we in the general public separate ideology from fact in this debate?
    - "Reagan's War: Who Won the Cold War?" No. UK725, 2002 November 11 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 84)
      Barton Bernstein, professor of history, Stanford University; Michael McFaul, Peter and Helen Bing research fellow, Hoover Institution, associate professor of political science, Stanford University, and author, Russia's Unfinished Revolution: Political Change from Gorbachev to Putin; and Peter Schweizer, research fellow, Hoover Institution and author, Reagan's War: The Epic Story of His Forty Year Struggle and Final Triumph over Communism. Did Ronald Reagan win the cold war? It's been a dozen years since its end--time enough to look back on the era with some historical perspective. And one question that historians continue to argue about is the role that Ronald Reagan, the man and his policies, played in bringing the cold war to an end. To what extent did Reagan's cold war strategy build on efforts of previous administrations and to what extent was it new? Did the Soviet Union collapse as a result of external pressure or internal weakness?
    - "The Population Bomb Redux: Is Population Growth a Problem?" No. UK726, 2002 November 12 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 85)
      Nicholas Eberstadt, visiting fellow, Center for Population and Developmental Studies, Harvard University and fellow, American Enterprise Institute; and Paul Ehrlich, Bing professor of population studies, Stanford University and author, The Population Bomb. In the past century the earth's human population has quadrupled, growing from 1.5 billion in 1900 to about 6 billion today. By 2050, it is estimated that the global population will reach 9 billion. In 1968, a young biologist named Paul Ehrlich wrote a best selling book called The Population Bomb, which sparked an ongoing debate about the dangers of overpopulation. He argued that population growth was destroying the ecological systems necessary to sustain life. So just how worried should we be? Is population growth a problem or not? And if so, what should we do about it?
    - "The Empire Strikes First? The National Security Strategy of the United States" No. UK727, 2003 January 16 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 85)
      Eliot Cohen, professor of strategic studies, School of Advanced International Studies, Johns Hopkins University, member, Defense Policy Board, and author, Supreme Command: Soldiers, Statesmen, and Leadership in Wartime; and Peter Tarnoff, United States undersecretary of state for political affairs (1993-1997), and former president, Council on Foreign Relations. In September 2002, President Bush released the first national security strategy report of his administration. Crafted by the President, his national security adviser, Condoleezza Rice, and a team of experts both inside and outside the government, the report lays out what some have called "the most important reformulation of U.S. grand strategy in more than half a century." Proponents say that the national security strategy presents the case for the responsible and justified use of American power, but critics call it a dangerous "doctrine without limits." Who's right?
    - "Debt and Taxes: The Bush Administration's Tax Plan" No. UK728, 2003 January 30 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 85)
      Michael Boskin, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, T. M. Friedman professor of economics, Stanford University, and chairman, President's Council of Economic Advisers (1989-1993); and Robert Reich, United States secretary of labor (1993-1997), university professor and Maurice B. Hexter professor of social and economic policy, Brandeis University, and author, I'll Be Short: Essentials for a Decent Working Society. In January 2003, the Bush administration unveiled a package of proposed new tax cuts, including provisions to eliminate the taxation of dividends and make permanent the 2001 tax cut. President Bush called the plan "an immediate boost to the economy" as well as "essential for the long run to lay the groundwork for future growth and prosperity." Critics have said that the plan doesn't provide short term economic stimulus and endangers long term growth and prosperity. Is the Bush tax plan good for the economy or not?
    - "Leadership in Wartime: Civilian Leaders in Time of War" No. UK729, 2003 January 16 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 85)
      Eliot Cohen, professor of strategic studies, School of Advanced International Studies, Johns Hopkins University, member, Defense Policy Board, and author, Supreme Command: Soldiers, Statesmen, and Leadership in Wartime; and David Kennedy, Donald J. McLachlan professor of history, Stanford University and Pulitzer Prize-winning author, Freedom from Fear: The American People in Depression and War, 1929-1945. In the modern democratic era, it's not uncommon for elected leaders to have little or no military training or experience. It has become an accepted notion that political leaders should therefore leave battle plans and campaign decisions to the military commanders and avoid micromanaging war. But is that notion correct? Or was Clemenceau right when he said that "war is too important to be left to the generals?" What lessons can we learn from studying the greatest wartime leaders, such as Lincoln, Churchill, and Franklin D. Roosevelt?
    - "Thinking Green or Thinking Greenbacks: President Bush's Environmental Policy" No. UK730, 2003 January 30 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 85)
      Terry L. Anderson, Martin and Illie Anderson senior fellow, Hoover Institution and executive director, Political Economy Research Center; and Mark Hertsgaard, journalist and author, The Eagle's Shadow: Why America Fascinates and Infuriates the World. During the 2000 presidential campaign, George W. Bush said, "Prosperity will mean little if we leave future generations a world of polluted air, toxic lakes and rivers, and vanished forests." So after two years in office, how has President Bush done as the chief steward of our nation's air, water, and land? Is the Bush environmental record the disaster that critics contend? Or has the administration just done a poor job of articulating its vision for new ways of caring for the environment
    - "Empire State Building? Is America Becoming an Empire?" No. UK731, 2003 February 28 (Folder VHS, box 15; Digital Betacam, box 86)
      Mark Danner, staff writer, New Yorker, professor, Graduate School of Journalism, University of California, Berkeley; and Niall Ferguson, professor of political and financial history, Jesus College, University of Oxford, and author, Empire: The Rise and Demise of the British World Order and the Lessons of Global Power. Since the end of the cold war, the world has watched as the United States became, not merely the world's only superpower, but what the French began calling a "hyperpower." Now with the United States asserting its will and power on such issues as Iraq and the war on terror while rejecting constraints that the international community tries to place on it, some suggest that the term American empire is more appropriate. If America does have an empire, it is not based on territorial expansion as in past empires. So what is it based on? And would taking on the role of imperial hegemony be good for America and the world?
    - "Behind Closed Doors: The Supreme Court and the Texas Homosexual Conduct Law" No. UK732, 2003 February 28 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 86)
      Pamela S. Karkan, Montgomery professor of public interest law, Stanford University; and Douglas W. Kmiec, dean and St. Thomas More professor of law, Columbus School of Law, Catholic University of America. A case currently before the Supreme Court challenges the constitutionality of the Texas Homosexual Conduct Law, which in 1974 legalized heterosexual sodomy but not same-sex sodomy. Does the Texas law violate the constitutional rights of homosexuals, or are states permitted to pass such laws if they choose? If the Supreme Court does strike down the Texas law, what implications will that have for other civil rights that gays and lesbians are seeking, such as same-sex marriage?
    - "Off to the Races: The Supreme Court and Affirmative Action" No. UK733, 2003 February 28 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 86)
      Vikram Amar, professor of law, Hastings College of Law, University of California; and Douglas W. Kmiec, dean and St. Thomas More professor of law, Columbus School of Law, Catholic University of America. The Supreme Court will soon announce its decisions on two cases that are being called the most important for affirmative action in a quarter century. These cases both challenge the use of racial preferences in the admissions policies at the University of Michigan. On one side of the legal dispute over the Michigan policies are those who argue that creating racial diversity on college campuses is a compelling interest that justifies the use of certain types of racial preferences in the admissions process. On the other side are those who argue that any system that rewards people solely on the basis of race is unconstitutional. Who's right? And how will the Supreme Court's decision affect the future of affirmative action?
    - "A Fork in the Road: Is the Transatlantic Alliance Dead?" No. UK734, 2003 March 12 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 86)
      Victor Davis Hanson, columnist, National Review Online, professor of classics and history, California State University, Fresno; and Charles Kupchan, senior fellow and director, European studies, Council on Foreign Relations, associate Professor, Walsh School of Foreign Service, Georgetown University, and author, The End of the American Era: U.S. Foreign Policy and the Geopolitics of the Twenty First Century. Over the past year, the clashes between the Bush administration and European leaders over the best way to handle Saddam Hussein have led many observers to suggest that the half-century-long alliance between Western Europe and the United States is dead. How serious is the rift between Europe and America, and why has it emerged? Is it still in the strategic interest of the United States to maintain tens of thousands of troops in Europe, or should we pull out of NATO altogether?
    - "Castles Made of Sand: The United States and Saudi Arabia" No. UK735, 2003 March 20 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 87)
      As'ad Abukhalil, professor of political science, California State University, Stanislaus; Daniel Pipes, director, Middle East Forum and columnist, New York Post and Jerusalem Post; and Abraham D. Sofaer, George P. Shultz senior fellow, Hoover Institution. Is Saudi Arabia an ally or an adversary? Saudi Arabia remains an autocratic monarchy, where the rights of women and the press are severely restricted. Saudi money is a principal source of funding for the Wahhabi sect, which promotes a militant form of Islam throughout the Muslim world. Osama bin Laden and fifteen of the nineteen participants in the attacks of September 11 came from Saudi Arabia. And yet, for more than 50 years, the United States has treated Saudi Arabia as an ally. Why? What role have Saudi oil and Saudi oil money played in shaping our relationship? Is it time to recognize that Saudi Arabia may threaten American national interests? If so, what should U.S. policy toward Saudi Arabia be?
    - "Carnage and Culture: The Western Way of War" No. UK736, 2003 March 12 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 87)
      Victor Davis Hanson, senior fellow, Hoover Institution, columnist, National Review Online, professor of classics and history, California State University, Fresno, and author, Carnage and Culture: Landmark Battles in the Rise of Western Power. Is the culture of the west, the line of cultural tradition that connects modern America and Europe with ancient Greece and Rome, particularly lethal in war? Victor Davis Hanson contends that, from the time of the Greeks on, western culture has created the deadliest soldiers in the history of civilization. What is it about the western tradition that has so often led to victory on the battlefield over non-Western armies? What does this tradition mean for the battles that America will face in the future?
    - "Pigs at the Trough? Restoring Confidence in Corporate America" No. UK737, 2003 March 20 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 87)
      David W. Brady, senior fellow and associate director for research, Hoover Institution and Bowen H. and Janice Arthur McCoy professor of political science and leadership values, Stanford Graduate School of Business; David R. Henderson, research fellow, Hoover Institution, associate professor, Graduate School of Business and Public Policy, Naval Postgraduate School, and author, The Joy of Freedom: An Economist's Odyssey; and Ariana Huffington, nationally syndicated columnist and author, Pigs at the Trough: How Corporate Greed and Political Corruption are Undermining America. A series of devastating accounting scandals at Enron, WorldCom, and Tyco, to name a few, have shaken the public's trust in the ethics and business practices of America's large corporations. What are the underlying factors behind this recent wave of scandals? Is deregulation the culprit? If so, do we need more regulation or merely better enforcement of existing regulations? Does the confluence of corporate lobbying and campaign contributions encourage corporate malfeasance? If so, what political reforms are necessary?
    - "The Whole World is Watching: Postwar Diplomacy" No. UK738, 2003 April 28 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 87)
      David Brooks, media fellow, Hoover Institution and senior editor, Weekly Standard; Christopher Hitchens, author and journalist, visiting professor of liberal studies, New School University; and Jan Kavan, president, United Nations General Assembly. Now that the war with Iraq is over, will our strained relations with our longtime European allies and the United Nations return to normal? Is that even desirable? Or are we witnessing the emergence of a fundamentally new structure of international relations?
    - "Great Expectations: Democracy in Iran" No. UK739, 2003 April 28 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 88)
      Michael McFaul, Peter and Helen Bing research fellow and associate professor of political science, Stanford University; Abbas Milani, visiting fellow, Hoover Institution and professor of history and political science, Notre Dame de Namur University; and Guity Nashat, research fellow, Hoover Institution and associate professor of history, University of Illinois, Chicago. It has been nearly twenty- five years since the Shah of Iran was overthrown in a popular revolution. The ensuing American hostage crisis marked the beginning of an era of mutual hostility between Iran and the United States--Iranian leader Ayatollah Khomeini often called the United States "the Great Satan"; more recently President Bush placed Iran on the so-called axis of evil. But an increasingly visible democratic reform movement supported by young Iranians born after the revolution suggests that Iran may be entering a new era of change. Just how powerful is the reform movement in Iran? And what should the United States do, if anything, to help bring about a new Iran?
  - Series 800, 2003-2004
    - "Peaceable Kingdom: Animal Rights" No. UK801, 2003 April 23 (Folder VHS, box 16; Digital Betacam, box 88; audio CD, box 56)
      David Blatte, animal law attorney; and Richard Epstein, Peter and Kirsten Bedford senior fellow, Hoover Institution and James Parker Hall distinguished service professor of law, University of Chicago. The past decade has seen the emergence of an increasingly vocal animal rights movement in this country. Although many of the specific goals of the movement have to do with promoting the humane treatment of animals, the underlying argument is that certain basic legal rights should be extended to animals as well. Should we recognize that animals have legal rights, or should we continue to regard animals as property, as resources to use as humans see fit? Just what rights, if any, should animals have? And how could these rights alter the relationship between humans and the rest of the animal kingdom?